<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
  <properties>
    <title>Introduction to the EGE framework</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <!-- The body of the document contains a number of sections -->
    <section name="Introduction to the EGE framework">
      <!-- Within sections, any XHTML can be used -->
      <p>The EGE is a major part of the ENRICH Garage system; its implementation is responsible for
        the management of conversions, transformations and validations of data performed by the
        ENRICH Garage. Conversions, transformations and validations are performed by a set of
        plug-ins compatible with the EGE plug-in specification. The software was initially created
        by the PSNC and OUCS as a part of the ENRICH project funded by the European Commission. EGE is
        distributed under an open-source license.</p>
      <p>The EGE is a framework. It provides definitions of plug-ins (building blocks) which can be
        used in combination to perform a series of operations. There is also the API that can be used
        by other applications utilizing EGE. The image below presents the overview of the EGE
        architecture.</p>
      <img src="images/ege-overview.png" alt="EGE Overview"/>

      <p>The use of the EGE is possible via the EGE API, which allows a program to:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>discover the functionality available for a particular data format that EGE provides with a current
          set of plug-ins;</li>
        <li>perform those available operations (e.g. conversion).</li>
      </ul>
      <p>There are three basic types of EGE plug-ins: Recognizer, Converter and Validator. </p>
      <ul>
        <li><b>Recognizer</b> - this plug-in is responsible for the recognition of the Internet
          Media Type (MIME type) of the given input data. For example, it will receive the input
          data and state that the input data has text/xml MIME type. The recognized data may then be
          further validated to check the format of the data.</li>
        <li><b>Validator</b> - this plug-in is responsible for validation of the input data. For
          example it may be used to validate the ENRICH TEI P5 data stored in a MIME type (e.g.
          text/xml) either received from end user or created by one of the converters. The following
          notation is assumed: ENRICH TEI P5 (text/xml) - it means that validator is able to
          validate ENRICH TEI P5 format encoded in text/xml.</li>
        <li><b>Converter</b> - this plug-in is responsible for converting the input data. It may be,
          for example, conversion from XML to Word, conversion from Word to PDF, conversion of the
          XML from one form to another (e.g. MASTER -> ENRICH TEI P5) or even cleaning the input
          data (e.g. removing redundant information).</li>
      </ul>
      <p>The idea is that there may be a number of implementations for each particular plug-in type
        (e.g. two recognizers, five converters and three validators) connected to EGE instance.
        Plug-ins are connected to the EGE automatically at the start time and can be combined to perform
        complex iterative operations. The extensions mechanism is based on the Java Plugin Framework
        (http://jpf.sourceforge.net/) library. Thanks to this approach it is possible for other interested parties to extend the
        EGE if desired. </p>
      <subsection name="EGE Projects">
        <p>Currently EGE consists of the following projects : </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <a href="multiprojects/ege-api/index.html">EGE API</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="multiprojects/ege-framework/index.html">EGE framework</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="multiprojects/ege-xsl-converter/index.html">EGE XSL converter</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="multiprojects/tei-converter/index.html">EGE TEI converter</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="multiprojects/ege-validator/index.html">EGE validator</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="multiprojects/ege-webservice/index.html">EGE RESTful web service</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="multiprojects/ege-webclient/index.html">EGE web client</a>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>

