<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>Introduction to the EGE Web Client</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Introduction to the EGE Web Client">

            <p> The ENRICH EGE Web Client gives an easy to use front end for exploiting the
                abilities of the ENRICH EGE. The ENRICH EGE is responsible for the management of
                conversions, transformations and validations of data performed by the ENRICH Garage.
                Conversions, transformations and validations are performed by a set of plug-ins
                compatible with the EGE plug-in specification. The software was initially created by
                the PSNC and OUCS as a part of the ENRICH project funded by the European Commission.
                EGE is distributed under an open-source license. It is straightforward and intuitive
                for users and has a clear progression through the steps needed to transform a
                document from one format to another. The EGE Web Client is a user-friendly frontend
                for the EGE Web Service but if one was converting many files, or doing so
                automatically as part of another process, it might be more appropriate to use the
                web service instead.</p>

            <subsection name="Using the EGE Web Client">
                <p>Main page of the EGE Web Client</p>
				<img src="images/ege-webclient1.png" alt="Main page of EGE Web Client"/>
				<p>The EGE Web Client should already have been set up and running as a web
                    application, all interaction with the EGE Web Client is through a web browser,
                    no extra software should be needed, however javascript must be enabled. To use
                    the EGE Web Client you go to the appropriate URL. In the case of the ENRICH
                    project this is: <a href="http://dlibra.psnc.pl/ege-webclient/"
                        >http://dlibra.psnc.pl/ege-webclient/</a> for the time being. If this has
                    not been set up, please go to the <a href="download.html">Download page</a>.
                    This webpage contains three tabs 'Conversion', 'Validation' and 'Help'. The last
                    of these links through to the help documentation, while the first two are where
                    one can undertake to use the main functions of the EGE Web Client.</p>
			</subsection>

            <subsection name="Converting Files with the EGE Web Client">
				<p>Sample EGE conversion panel </p>
				<img src="images/ege-webclient2.png" alt="Sample EGE conversion panel"/>
                <p>The EGE Web Client allows you to convert documents from one format to another,
                    possibly using an intermediate format before a second conversion. To know what
                    forms of document it can convert to, the EGE Web Client needs to establish what
                    format the input document is in. Once it knows this it can offer a conversion
                    path, and allow a choice between multiple conversion profiles, before converting
                    your file.</p>

                <h4>Selecting Input Type</h4>
                <p>The EGE Web Client allows you to specify an input document's type from a list of
                    choices predefined by the conversions that have been installed into that
                    instance of the EGE Web Client. In the case of the ENRICH EGE Web Client
                    conversion service these are: </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>TEI,text/xml</li>
                    <li>TEI,application/msword</li>
                    <li>MASTER,text/xml</li>
                    <li>EAD,text/xml</li>
                </ul>
                <p> This takes the format of:<br/>
                    <b>
                        <source>FORMAT,INTERNET MIME TYPE (IMT)</source>
                    </b><br/> So in the case of the ENRICH EGE Web Client conversion service there
                    are three formats TEI, MASTER, and EAD, and only two different IMT's text/xml
                    and application/msword that it knows how to handle as input types. The EGE will
                    test and validate your document after uploading it against its definition for
                    the format you select.</p>
                <p>
                    <b>Please note that the MS Word format referred to here is the DOCX format.
                        Earlier word formats will cause an error.</b>
                </p>


                <h4>Selecting Conversion Path</h4>
                <p>The conversion path is the route through which the EGE can transform your
                    documents to other formats. This may simply be a single conversion or involve
                    more than one steps. For example, having chosen 'TEI,text/xml' as the input
                    type, one of the options available to us for conversion is: <br/>
                    <b>
                        <source>I:TEI,text/xml/O:TEI,application/msword(TEI Converter) </source>
                    </b><br/> The 'I:' section of this path indicates the IMT input type of the
                    document to be converted. In this case it is "TEI,text/xml". This is followed by
                    the output format indicated by 'O:'. In this case that format is:
                    "TEI,application/msword(TEI Converter)". This shows that our input document
                    which is in TEI XML will be converted to MS Word using the TEI converter (which
                    transforms TEI files to the docx format). The reverse of this would be from MS
                    Word to TEI: <br/>
                    <b>
                        <source>I:TEI,application/msword/O:TEI,text/xml(TEI Converter)</source>
                    </b><br/>
                </p>

                <p>One of the great strengths of the EGE is that it allows multiple transformations
                    through a variety of formats. For example, the following path: <br/>
                    <b>
                        <source> I:TEI,application/msword/O:TEI,text/xml(TEI Converter)->I:TEI,text/xml/O:TEI,application/xhtml+xml(TEI Converter)  </source>
                    </b><br/> details the conversion path from an MS Word document to TEI XML, and
                    then (after the arrow '->' indicating a second step in the path), the XML that
                    results from the first transformation becomes the input to a conversion from TEI
                    XML to XHTML. </p>

                <h4>Conversion Profiles</h4>
                <p>Beneath the selection of a conversion the EGE Web Client gives you the
                    opportunity to modify the conversion path parameters through the selection of a
                    predefined conversion profile. In the ENRICH EGE Web Client this gives you a
                    choice between 'default', 'enrich' and 'iso' conversion profiles. One drop-down
                    selection box for a profile will appear for each major step in the chosen
                    conversion path. If you have not set up any conversion profiles for your own
                    project, then using 'default' is probably the most sensible. </p>

                <h4>Converting Your File</h4>
                <p> Underneath where you select the conversion profiles you are prompted to "Specify
                    file to convert:" and there is a 'Browse' but to look through your computer's
                    file system to find a file of the selected input type to convert. Make sure that
                    the document you select is in the correct format, and click on the 'Convert'
                    button. </p>
                <p>If your file has been converted successfully, you will be prompted to download
                    it. If it has failed to convert and error message will be displayed. Make a note
                    of this error message for any bug report you want to submit before trying again
                    after ensure the correct input format has been chosen.</p>

            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Validating Files with the EGE Web Client">
				<p>EGE validation panel </p>
				<img src="images/ege-webclient3.png" alt="EGE validation panel"/>
                <p>In addition to converting your files, the EGE can simply be used to validate your
                    files to ensure they are the correct input format. This takes place
                    automatically when you upload your files for conversion, but it is also
                    available as a separate feature on a second tab in the EGE Web Client.</p>

                <h4>Selecting Input Type</h4>
                <p>Similar to the 'Conversion' tab, the EGE Web Client validation service allows you
                    to specify an input document's type from a list of choices predefined by the
                    conversions that have been installed into that instance of the EGE Web Client.
                    In the case of the ENRICH EGE Web Client these are: </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>TEI,text/xml</li>
                    <li>MASTER,text/xml</li>
                    <li>EAD,text/xml</li>
                </ul>
                <p>Note that MS Word is not an option for validation because the validation method
                    deails with 'text/xml' files. So in the case of the ENRICH EGE Web Client
                    validation service there are three formats TEI, MASTER, and EAD, and only one
                    IMT's "text/xml" that it knows how to handle as input types. The EGE will test
                    and validate your document after uploading it against its definition for the
                    format you select.</p>

                <h4>Validating Your File</h4>
                <p> Underneath where you select the conversion profiles you are prompted to "Select
                    file:" to validate and there is a 'Browse' but to look through your computer's
                    file system to find a file of the selected input type to validate. Make sure
                    that the document you select is in the correct format, and click on the
                    'Validate' button. </p>
                <p>If your file has been validated successfully a message will appear indicating
                    this success. If it has failed to validate the error message will be displayed.
                    Make a note of this error message for any bug report you want to submit and
                    correcting whatever the error is before trying again after ensuring the correct
                    input format has been chosen.</p>

            </subsection>




        </section>
    </body>
</document>

